<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Fabian Köhler - Publications</title><link href="https://fkoehler.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://fkoehler.org/feeds/publications.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://fkoehler.org/</id><updated>2021-04-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Bosonic quantum dynamics following colliding potential wells</title><link href="https://fkoehler.org/publications/2021-colliding-wells.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-20T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>F. Köhler</name></author><id>tag:fkoehler.org,2021-04-20:/publications/2021-colliding-wells.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We explore the dynamics of two interacting bosons confined in colliding potential wells using MCTDHB unraveling the fundamental processes that take place.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We employ the multiconfiguration time-dependent Hartree method for bosons in order to investigate the correlated nonequilibrium quantum dynamics of two bosons confined in two colliding and uniformly accelerated Gaussian wells. As the wells approach each other an effective, transient double-well structure is formed. This induces a transient and oscillatory over-barrier transport. We monitor both the amplitude of the intrawell dipole mode in the course of the dynamics as well as the final distribution of the particles between the two wells. For fast collisions we observe an emission process which we attribute to two distinct mechanisms. Energy transfer processes lead to an untrapped fraction of bosons and a resonant enhancement of the deconfinement for certain kinematic configurations can be observed. Despite the comparatively weak interaction strengths employed in this work, we identify strong interparticle correlations by analyzing the corresponding von Neumann entropy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Publications"></category></entry><entry><title>Dynamical Pruning of the Non-Equilibrium Quantum Dynamics of Trapped Ultracold Bosons</title><link href="https://fkoehler.org/publications/2019-dynamical-pruning.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>F. Köhler</name></author><id>tag:fkoehler.org,2019-08-05:/publications/2019-dynamical-pruning.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The exponentially growing Hilbert space of many-body systems as a function of system sizes poses a major challenge for numerical methods. We explore how a dynamical pruning approach can be employed within the framework of MCTDHB in order to reduce the computational effort.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The investigation of the nonequilibrium quantum dynamics of bosonic many-body systems is very challenging due to the excessively growing Hilbert space and poses a major problem for their theoretical description and simulation. We present a novel dynamical pruning approach in the framework of the multiconfiguration time-dependent Hartree method for bosons (MCTDHB) to tackle this issue by dynamically detecting the most relevant number states of the underlying physical system and modifying the many-body Hamiltonian accordingly. We discuss two different number state selection criteria as well as two different ways to modify the Hamiltonian. Our scheme regularly re-evaluates the number state selection in order to dynamically adapt to the time evolution of the system. To benchmark our methodology, we study the nonequilibrium dynamics of bosonic particles confined either in an optical lattice or in a double-well potential. It is shown that our approach reproduces the unpruned MCTDHB results accurately while yielding a significant reduction of the simulation time. The speedup is particularly pronounced in the case of the optical lattice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Publications"></category></entry></feed>